Shwetha Rajaram

shwethar@umich.edu shwetharajaram.github.io University of Michigan, Ann Arbor School of Information

Overview

My research explores how to enable non-technical users to create AR/VR experiences while guiding them towards safer and more privacy-friendly design. To do this, I develop and evaluate AR/VR authoring tools and design methods that educate users about potential safety, security & privacy harms and equip them with tools to mitigate these issues.

Research interests: human-computer interaction (HCI), augmented & virtual reality (AR/VR), creativity support tools, privacy & security

Education

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

SEPT 2020 - present

Ph.D. in Information

Advisor: Prof. Michael Nebeling

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

SEPT 2015 - MAY 2019

B.S.E. in Computer Science & Engineering

Publications

Peer-Reviewed Full Papers

Shwetha Rajaram, Michael Nebeling. Paper Trail: An Immersive Authoring System for Augmented Reality Instructional Experiences.

CHI 2022

Michael Nebeling, <u>Shwetha Rajaram</u>, Liwei Wu, Yifei Cheng, Jaylin Herskovitz. XRStudio: A Virtual Production and Live Streaming System for Immersive

CHI 2021

Instructional Experiences.

Michael Nebeling, Maximillian Speicher, Xizi Wang, Shwetha Rajaram, Brian	CHI 2020
D. Hall, Zijian Xie, Alexander R. E. Raistrick, Michelle Aebersold, Edward G.	
Happ, Jiayin Wang, Yanan Sun, Lotus Zhang, Leah E. Ramsier, Rhea Kulkarni.	
MRAT: The Mixed Reality Analytics Toolkit. Best Paper Award	

Workshop Papers

<u>Shwetha Rajaram</u> , Michael Nebeling. <i>Extending AR Authoring Tools with</i>	SSPXR @
Built-in Support for Privacy and Security Analysis.	CHI 2022
Shwetha Rajaram, Franziska Roesner, Michael Nebeling. Designing	VR4Sec @
Privacy-Informed Sharing Techniques for Multi-User Augmented Reality.	SOUPS 2021

Teaching Experience

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

Graduate Student Instructor, SI 659: Developing AR/VR Experiences	JAN 2022 - present
Graduate Student Instructor, SI 559: Introduction to AR/VR Application Design	SEPT - DEC 2021
Instructional Aide, EECS 493: User Interface Development	JAN 2019 - MAY 2019

Professional Experience

JP Morgan Chase, Jersey City, NJ	JAN - DEC 2018
Software Engineering Intern	
John Deere, Moline, IL Information Technology Intern	MAY - AUG 2017

Awards

CHI 2020 Best Paper Award	MAY 2020
Society of Women Engineers Outstanding Collegiate Member	OCT 2019

MLK Spirit Awa	rd, UM	College	of Engine	ering
TITEL COPILIE / TITE	,	201122	01 -1101110	~ · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · ·

IAN 2019

Service

Assistant to Program Chairs

UIST 2021

Reviewing

ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)

2021-2022

IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR)

2021

Leadership & Outreach

Washtenaw Elementary Science Olympiad (WESO)

SEP 2011 - present

Event Supervisor

Society of Women Engineers (SWE) at UMich

APR 2016 - APR 2019

President, Executive Board Secretary, Executive Board Summer Engineering Exploration Camp Director Elementary Outreach Officer

Women+ Excelling More in Mathematics, Engineering and APR 2016 - present Science (F.E.M.M.E.S.)

Website Developer Capstone Activities Coordinator Volunteer

Academic Mentoring

Jihee Yoon, University of Michigan School of Information (Masters) JAN 2022 - APR 2020

Chen Chen, University of Michigan School of Information (Masters)

JUNE 2021 - APR 2020

Sereen Kallerackal, University of Michigan School of Information FEB - APR 2021 (Masters)

Maya Subramanian, University of Michigan Computer Science JAN - MAR 2021 (Undergraduate)

Skills

Research Methods: HCI systems research, mixed-methods user studies, user-driven elicitation, interviews, focus groups

Programming Languages: C#, HTML/Javascript, C++, Python

AR/VR Technologies

SDKs: Unity Engine (ARFoundation, Vuforia, MRTK) and A-Frame

Devices: mobile AR, HoloLens 1/2, Oculus Rift, Windows Mixed Reality headsets

Coursework

Ph.D. Courses

Privacy in Information Technology, Human-Computer Interaction, Research Methods, Human-Al Interaction, Algorithms & Societal Implications, Introduction to Statistics and Data Analysis, Doctoral Foundation Seminar (*Information Science Theory*), Educational Technology Design

Masters in Information Courses

Developing AR/VR Experiences, Engineering Interactive Systems, Contextual Inquiry, Graphic Design, Fundamentals of Human Behavior, Game Development Research, Independent Study (AR/VR)

Selected Undergraduate Courses

Game Development, User Interface Development, Web Systems, Intro to Computer Security, Intro to Machine Learning, Data Structures and Algorithms, Intro to Computer Organization, Intro to Computer Science Theory, Interaction Design, Drawing